Hello, my friends, are welcome to exercise number 123 in this exercise.
We are going to implement and create the binary search class in Java, and we will see how the algorithm
binary search algorithm works in Java by creating it in a recursive way and an iterative way.
So I would create a new class here called binary
binary search.
And this class will contain the recursive waited for the there and the iteratively so imperative
derivative way and the recursive way.
So how to do that, we start by making an input.
This is public and the returning type of this function public end.
And I will call it binary
searching.
Iterative.
OK took into the parameter, the array that we have going to search for inside it and index that it
is presenting the variable that we are going to search for and in-flow that lower index of the array
and end hide the higher index of only.
So here we will repeat, repeat here, repeat until that point was low and high, met each other because
we need to do segment and partition that array into two pieces or worse until we have only one piece
that's representing the low and the high.
And this is are met each other.
So while Lou, because you are using the iterative and low less than or equal to high, then what to
do?
We will create an end made here equal to no.
Plus high minus low here and
over two.
And then I will create if array at index mid here, equal equal to X, then return it.
OK, if this is a case of we have segmented the array and in a four is for like a lucky one, we have
the array at index middle equal to the X that the outgoing search for otherwise if array at index mid
less than X, then.
No equal to net plus one as
high as equal to men, minus one.
OK, then here.
This is the wide loop we need to get the first element, which the first condition, which is the middle
of the era.
If that rate at middle, then X then get the left, otherwise get the right path.
If we have met the X over the low and the high and this is together and we don't return anything, then
we need to return minus one that indicates that there is no element in such case, so no element.
So the element is not found inside.
Their Element X is not found in the array array, which is returning the minus one case.
OK, let's test this program and test its possible ways.
So I will create here public static void main and I will make here string
args.
I will create an object of this Class B as I search equal to new binary search and we start by entering
every year equal to
these other variables and equal to a dot length.
And we start here.
So Int X equal to four int the result equal to binary search dot binary searching, iterative way past
with past X with past the lower bound of the array index, which is zero and then minus one, which
is the high.
So if a result equal equal to minus one,
then system out the trend
not found.
It's very simple.
Otherwise, we will present out
element
found at index clusters.
OK, let's run and see.
We are searching for a number for inside this Saturday.
So the result would be not found if we are searching for here like three.
Let's run and see.
Oops!
So there is some error.
OK, we are here.
From binary search.
OK, so.
And this result not found is very logic because we don't pass and assorted array.
So this would be confusing for a non sorted thing.
Let's search again for this and let's run.
And the element is found at Index three, so we start from here no less than or equal to high.
And we made all of this condition checking this because we need a sorted array in order to start segmenting
like we have segmented.
Here are the five.
So these elements, these elements are not useful.
We segment it here.
We are searching for four.
So we segment it four to remove them.
And now three, which is not used and having one element which is presented and returning value of its
ethics.
So in this way, we have created that binary search inside interactive way.
OK, now let's see if the recursive way
we start by making public static void or ends in the same way we start by finally searching for recursive.
They're going to of the array if they're going to search inside it and exit that, you can't go and
search for enclosed and compact.
But this time is very different because we need we are passing the elements low and the high index and
y and a recursive way.
So the function call itself LA high, equal or greater than equal to low that we make the text the integer
made variable, which is equal to low plus high minus low over two.
We calculate it and now we're.
But if found at MIT, then returned it.
If they at Index Med equals equal to X, then what to do?
We were at MIT.
Otherwise we will search the left path.
So if array at index net
greater than X, then we will return binary searching recursive method.
And we pass the array here that x low and mid minus one.
This is the trick the first string, which is made minus one.
Now we will search the right half
if or we can make a return.
Made the plus one now the low and high is the same.
So here is the trick.
The first time we passed for when we have searched the left half the high as middle minus swan and when
we search for the right half, we return.
We are past them low as mitt plus one and the high equal to high.
OK, otherwise we will return minus one in case we don't found that.
Let's go up and test the this in the main function that we have created before, but in this time we
need to store here.
Binary searching, not iterative.
We've passed the recursive Arc zero array x zero and minus one.
Let's run and see.
And here we go.
We have the element found that in this story, which is here, there we are searching for, for and
everything is working fine.
So in this exercise, we have learned about the binary search search in a recursive way and in iterative
way.
And we have learned about this example and we have learned that it's very important to pass sorted.